window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Digital_Logic - Number_System — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Number_System — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider three registers R1, R2, and R3 that store numbers in IEEE-754 single precision floating point format. Assume that R1 and R2 contain the values (in hexadecimal notation) 0x42200000 and 0xC1200000, respectively. <br><br>\nIf \\(R3=\\frac{R1}{R2}\\), what is the value stored in R3? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0x40800000</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0xC0800000</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0x83400000</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0xC8500000</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>0xC0800000</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333202/gate2020-cs-29#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider Z = X - Y where X, Y and Z are all in sign-magnitude form. X and Y are each represented in n bits. To avoid overflow, the representation of Z would require a minimum of: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>n-1 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>n+1 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n+2 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>n+1 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302840/gate2019-cs-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>In 16-bit 2's complement representation, the decimal number -28 is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1111 1111 0001 1100</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0000 0000 1110 0100</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1111 1111 1110 0100</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1000 0000 1110 0100</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1111 1111 1110 0100</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302844/gate2019-cs-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>A computer uses ternary system instead of the traditional systen, An n bit string in the binary system will occupy <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3+n ternary digits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2n/3 ternary digits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(n \\log _{2} 3\\) ternary digits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(n \\log _{3} 2\\) ternary digits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(n \\log _{3} 2\\) ternary digits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213556/isro2018-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Given \\(\\sqrt{224_{r}}=13_{r}\\) the value of radix r is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213569/isro2018-19\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>If a variable can take only integral values from 0 to n, where n is an integer, then the variable can be represented as a bit-field whose width is (the log in the answer are to the base 2, and \\(\\lceil\\log n\\rceil\\) means the floor of \\(\\log_{}{n}\\) ) <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\log (n) \\right \\rceil + 1 \\text{ bits}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\log (n-1) \\right \\rceil + 1 \\text{ bits}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\log (n+1) \\right \\rceil + 1\\text{ bits}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213585/isro2018-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider the unsigned 8-bit fixed point binary Number System below, <br><br>\n\\(b_7  b_6  b_5  b_4  b_3 .  b_2  b_1  b_0\\) <br><br>\nwhere the position of the binary point is between \\(b_3 \\; and \\; b_2\\). Assume \\(b_7\\) is the most significant bit. Some of the decimal numbers listed below cannot be represented exactly in the above representation: <br><br>\n(i) 31.500 (ii) 0.875 (iii) 12.100 (iv) 3.001 <br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>None of (i), (ii), (iii), (iv) can be exactly represented</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only (ii) cannot be exactly represented</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only (iii) and (iv) cannot be exactly represented</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only (i) and (ii) cannot be exactly represented</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Only (iii) and (iv) cannot be exactly represented</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204107/gate2018-33#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>\\((1217)_{8}\\) is equivalent to <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((1217)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((028F)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((2297)_{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((0B17)_{16}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((028F)_{16}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1297/gate2009-5-isro2017-57\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>When two n-bit binary numbers are added the sum will contain at the most <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n  bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>n+2 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>n+3 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n+1 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>n+1 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128641/isro2017-24\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Given the following binary number in 32-bit (single precision) IEEE-754 format:<br>\n00111110011011010000000000000000<br>\nThe decimal value closest to this floating- point number is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1.45 * \\(10^{1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1.45 * \\(10^{-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2.27 * \\(10^{-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2.27 * \\(10^{1}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2.27 * \\(10^{-1}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118434/gate2017-2-12#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>The representation of the value of a 16-bit unsigned integer X in hexadecimal number system\nis BCA9. The representation of the value of X in octal number system is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>571244</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>736251</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>571247</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>136251</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>136251</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118337/gate2017-2-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>The n-bit fixed-point representation of an unsigned real number real X uses f bits for the\nfraction part. Let i=n-f. The range of decimal values for X in this representation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(2^{-f} \\; to \\;  2^{i}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{-f} \\; to \\; (2^{i}-2^{-f})\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(0 \\; to \\;  2^{i}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(0 \\; to \\;  (2^{i}-2^{-f})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(0 \\; to \\;  (2^{i}-2^{-f})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118287/gate2017-1-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following binary number is the same as its 2's complement ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1010</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(0101\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1000</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1001</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1000</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/55458/isro2016-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The Excess-3 code is also called <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Cyclic Redundancy Code</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Weighted Code</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Self-Complementing Code</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Algebraic Code</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Self-Complementing Code</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/56034/isro2016-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If \\((12A7C)_{16} = (X)_8\\) then the value of X is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>224174</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>425174</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6173</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>225174</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>225174</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/56071/isro2016-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
